This is one of the strongest
partnerships in Asia. It's described by
both governments as an all-weather
strategic cooperative partnership. It
stretches across almost every sector.
China brings capital and invests in
infrastructure and industry. Pakistan
offers a growing market and a strategic
gateway to the region. Now this
relationship is reaching a new level.
Pandas and space. So, what's going on?
Let's start with pandas, but not these
pandas. We're talking panda bonds.
>> Islamic Republic of Pakistan is proud to
be the first panda bond issuer from
South Asia.
>> But what exactly is a panda bond?
Countries borrow in foreign currencies
all the time. Usually, it's US dollars,
which they use to pay for lots of
important things. One way they borrow is
through government bonds. That's when a
government borrows cash and promises to
pay it back with interest. More and more
firms and governments are borrowing from
investors in China instead. And they're
doing that by issuing bonds in China's
currency, the renmi, also known as the
yuan. These bonds are called panda
bonds.
Pakistan is starting small with an
initial issuance of $250 million. It's
the first step in a planned $1 billion
program.
But compared to IMF loans, trade flows
or remittances, how much of a difference
can $250 million really make?
>> If you compare with other external
sources of financing, whether it's
public or private, uh it's an
insignificant amount, $250 million, but
it's not at the same time uh it's
Pakistan efforts to diversify
different means of financing. The money
is to be used to fund projects in water
management, social infrastructure and
education. But beyond financing green
projects, this first bond is also
playing a different role.
>> This is not about only to raise money
from the Chinese investors. But it is
also an effort to integrate in the
Chinese market.
>> Now the second thing space.
Ever since we have launched
our space program, I would now say that
our friendship is touching the skies. In
April, China launched a Pakistan
developed observation satellite into
orbit. For Pakistan, the potential goes
far beyond prestige.
>> You cannot overemphasize the
the importance to Pakistan in terms of
respectability.
This is a country which is economically
struggling but trying to you know make
make amends and move on and all of a
sudden now they've gone to space.
>> In 2025 alone floods caused an estimated
$2.9 billion in damage. In 2022 the
losses were around $30 billion.
Pakistan hopes satellite data can help
improve disaster management and urban
planning.
But that's only one potential benefit.
Two Pakistani astronauts are training
with their Chinese counterparts. One of
them is expected to travel to China's
space station as a payload specialist.
So for me that's where the potential
rises um because in terms of
um making or providing
Pakistani collaborators, researchers the
opportunity
to tap into that market which wasn't
there for them. the access that they can
have then they can use for their own
advantage. So I think that's where the
profitability for Pakistan will come in.
But while space cooperation is still
about potential, the biggest test of
China Pakistan economic relations
remains much closer to Earth.
Let's look at the pillar of this
relationship. The China Pakistan
economic corridor better known as Cpek.
A multi-billion dollar flagship project
of China's belt and road initiative. A
decade later has it lived up to
expectations.
>> Pakistan was expecting that CPAC could
contribute 2 to 2.5% of its GDP.
Pakistan was expecting that there the
industrial cooperation of CPEC uh
Chinese industrial industries will be re
relocated in Pakistan and they will
create lots of jobs for Pakistan.
Pakistan will become a manufacturing hub
etc. That has not materialized so far.
>> What did materialize though was energy.
Before the launch of CPEC, Pakistan
faced severe electricity shortages. But
within a decade, installed electricity
capacity had doubled from around 23,500
megawatt to more than 46,500.
Pakistan is producing surplus energy. On
paper, that's a success. But there's a
catch. Electricity is expensive.
In the contracts they would that would
sign, they were uh take or pay. So
whether Pakistan utilizes uh consumes
this energy or not, Pakistan must pay
Chinese investors. So it created a huge
problem for Pakistan and now it has
become kind of a liability.
>> So if energy didn't transform the
economy, what about trade? China is
Pakistan's largest trading partner.
Between July 2025 and January 2026,
China exported nearly$13 billion worth
of goods to Pakistan. In the other
direction, Pakistan exported just around
$ 1.5 billion dollars to China.
To put it another way, Pakistan imports
nine times more from China than China
does from Pakistan. There's no doubt
that the economic relationship between
China and Pakistan is deep and
multifaceted. It now stretches from
roads and power plants to defense, panda
bonds, and even space cooperation. But
one lesson keeps coming up. Part of the
problem is the narrative because I
politicians like to sell projects
especially if nothing is happening they
will oversell it.
Over the past 75 years Pakistan China
ties have expanded across every sector.
While this has delivered clear economic
and strategic benefits for Islamabad, it
has also increased Pakistan's reliance
on Beijing for investment, finance and
technological cooperation.